Montgomery Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Montgomery Family Papers 1771-1974 1858-1974
MSS56630
Montgomery family
12,000 items
33 containers
13.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, speeches and writings, financial papers, newspaper clippings and miscellany of various members of the Montgomery family, especially Giles Foster Montgomery (1835-1888) and Emily Redington Montgomery (1839-1898). Includes papers of allied Peck and Perkins families relating to the experiences of members in the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Borglum, Gutzon, 1867-1941--Correspondence.; Borglum, Mary--Correspondence.; Cummings, Homer S. (Homer Stillé), 1870-1956--Correspondence.; Draper, Ernest Gallaudet, 1885-1954--Correspondence.; Franklin, John L. (John Lester), 1856-1901--Correspondence.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928--Correspondence.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924--Correspondence.; Meyer, Eugene, 1875-1959--Correspondence.; Montgomery family.; Montgomery, Emily Redington, 1839-1898. Emily Redington Montgomery papers.; Montgomery, George Redington, 1870-1945. George Redington Montgomery papers.; Montgomery, Giles Foster, 1835-1888. Giles Foster Montgomery papers.; Montgomery, Marshall Hugh, 1909-2000. Marshall Hugh Montgomery papers.; Peck family.; Peck, Frank Henry, 1836-1864--Correspondence.; Perkins family.; Perkins, Newton William, 1839-1902--Correspondence.; Trowbridge, J. A. (James A.), Jr.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Armenia America Society.; Aubrey G. Langston & Co.; Inter-allied Commission on Mandates in Turkey. American Section.; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); United States. Army--Military life.; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 12th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 13th (1862-1866)
Subjects
Banks and banking--New York (State)--New York.; Missions--Turkey.; Securities--New York (State)--New York.
Places
Connecticut--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Fort Jackson (La.)--History--Siege, 1862.; Fort Saint Philip (La.)--History.; Louisiana--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; New Orleans (La.)--History--Capture, 1862.; New Orleans (La.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Turkey--Social conditions.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Washington (D.C.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Acquisition Information
The papers of the Montgomery family were given to the Library of Congress by Marshall H. Montgomery in 1975.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Montgomery family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Giles Foster Montgomery
Date Event
1835, Nov. 8 Born, Walden, Vt.
1860 Graduated, Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vt.
1863 Graduated, Lane Seminary, Cincinnati, Ohio Married Emily Redington Sailed to Turkey as a missionary
1864 Stationed at Adana, Turkey
1865 Transferred to Marash, Turkey
1883 Returned to Adana, Turkey
1885 Assumed pastorate, Phoenix, Oswego Co., N.Y.
1886 Returned to Adana, Turkey
1888 Died, Adana, Turkey
Emily Redington Montgomery
Date Event
1839, Aug. 2 Born, Moscow, N.Y.
1863 Married Giles Foster Montgomery Sailed to Turkey as missionary
1876 Visited the United States
1877 Returned to Marash, Turkey
1883 Transferred to Adana, Turkey
1884 Returned to the United States
1887 Returned to Adana, Turkey
1888 Moved to New Haven, Conn.
1892 Returned to Turkey
1898, Feb. 19 Died, Beirut, Syria
George Redington Montgomery
Date Event
1870, June 17 Born, Marash, Turkey
1892 A.B., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1894 LL.B., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1897 War correspondent, London Standard, and special correspondent, London Daily Graphic, London England
1897 1898 Student, University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany
1900 B.D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1900 1904 Lecturer, Department of Philosophy, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1901 Ph.D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn. Ordained Congregationalist minister
1901 1904 Pastor, Olivet Church, Bridgeport, Conn.
1902 Married Emily E. Emerson (died 1903)
1903 Published The Place of Values. Bridgeport, Conn.: G. R. Montgomery
1904 1905 Professor of philosophy, Carleton College, Northfield, Minn.
1906 1916 Assistant minister, Madison Square Presbyterian Church, New York, N.Y.
1907 Married Helen M. Perkins
1910 Published The Unexplored Self. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons
1911 1918 Lecturer, New York University, New York, N.Y.
1916 Special assistant to the United States ambassador, Constantinople, Turkey
1917 Air service, Paris, France
1918 Secretary of Paris Division, YMCA Attached to Paris Peace Conference
1919 Technical adviser, Inter-allied Commission on Mandates in Turkey (King-Crane Commission)
1919 1920 Assistant professor of French, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1920 1923 Director, Armenia America Society
1925 1940 Pastor, Noroton Presbyterian Church, Darien, Conn.
1929 1945 Editorial writer, Stamford Advocate
1940 1945 Pastor emeritus, Noroton Presbyterian Church, Darien, Conn.
1942 Published English Language Sounds. Stamford, Conn.: R. Montgomery Publishing Co.
1945, Nov. 29 Died, Stamford, Conn.
Marshall Hugh Montgomery
Date Event
1909, May 16 Born, New York
1931 B.A., Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vt.
1933 Married Prudence B. Ingham
1931 1940 Discount banker, New York Hanseatic Corp.
1940 1951 Secretary, D. W. Rich & Co.
1951 1974 Vice president, Aubrey G. Langston & Co. Member, American Stock Exchange
2000, Oct. 11 Died, Delray Beach, Fla.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Montgomery family record the activities of five generations of the family and also include two smaller groups of papers belonging to the Peck and Perkins families that were merged with the Montgomery family by the marriage of George Redington Montgomery to Helen M. Perkins in 1907. The collection spans the years 1771-1974, with the bulk of the material from 1858 to 1974, and is organized into three series: Peck Family Papers, Perkins Family Papers, and Montgomery Family Papers. Included are correspondence, speeches and writings, financial papers, newspaper clippings, a large assemblage of miscellany, and a special segment of correspondence and papers relating to the work of the Inter-allied Commission on Mandates in Turkey (King-Crane Commission) after World War I and the Armenia-America Society.
The Peck Family Papers are primarily those of Frank Henry Peck, a maternal cousin of Helen Perkins Montgomery. Although the Peck Family Papers cover the years 1771-1946, most are concentrated within the period 1856-1864 and consist of correspondence between Frank Peck and his mother and brother. The letters written between 1856 and 1857 are concerned with his first job as a teacher following his graduation from Yale University. The first of the Civil War letters, written in the spring of 1862 after he had joined the 12th Connecticut Infantry Regiment, reflect the anxiety and trepidation that the new recruit felt in anticipation of his first encounter with the enemy. Later letters contain accounts of troop activities and reconnoitering expeditions, and the letters of April 19 and 30 and May 4, 1862, describe in detail the bombardment of Fort Jackson and Fort Saint Philip, and finally, the capitulation of the city of New Orleans. Some of the letters written during this period are good sources for impressions and accounts of the military occupation of New Orleans.
The Perkins Family Papers span the years 1832-1953, but the nucleus of the series is the Civil War correspondence of Newton William Perkins written between 1861 and 1866. Perkins, the father of Helen Perkins Montgomery, was a colonel and later brevet major with the 13th Connecticut Infantry Regiment. His letters, written from on board various ships and from different camps, trace the movement of his regiment from Connecticut to New Orleans and back to Washington, D.C., and Virginia as changes were made in the strategy of the war. The letters also recount his daily duties and experiences and describe the general hardships endured by the soldiers. Some regimental muster rolls and papers from his service as provost marshal are included in the collection.
The series of Montgomery Family Papers extend from 1858 to 1974 and are centered around George Redington Montgomery and Marshall Hugh Montgomery. The closeness that existed between the members of the family is reflected in family correspondence forming about one third of the series. The letters generally relate to family matters, but also touch on other areas. Emily Redington Montgomery's letters to her children are significant for their glimpses of Turkey during the awakening of national consciousness among the countries of the Ottoman Empire. They contain references to the treatment of non-Muslims, mention uprisings in various towns, and provide insight into the difficulties of operating a Christian mission school in Turkey during the reign of Abdul-Hamid II, Sultan of the Turks. George Redington Montgomery's letters to his family during 1918-1919 report his observations on America's participation in the Paris Peace Conference after World War I and comment on the attitudes and objectives of the Allied Powers at the conference.
The bulk of the general correspondence in the Montgomery Family Papers series consists of letters received and a few copies of letters sent by George Redington Montgomery; Mary Borglum (daughter of Giles Foster Montgomery and Emily Redington Montgomery) and her husband, Gutzon Borglum; and Marshall Hugh Montgomery. Those of George Montgomery relate to the development of his career and to his church activities. Correspondents include James Trowbridge, Robert Lansing, John L. Franklin, Ernest Gallaudet Draper, Eugene Meyer, Homer S. Cummings, and Henry Cabot Lodge (1850-1924). Most of Mary's letters are to and from friends, although some of the later ones pertain to her financial problems. The letters of Marshall are a commentary on his standing in the community. They show his support of community and public service projects, his participation in local government, and his interest in local history.
The business papers in the Montgomery Family Papers contain correspondence and printed matter covering the thirty years Marshall Hugh Montgomery served as a dealer in securities on Wall Street where he pioneered the use of repurchase agreements. For the most part, the papers contain little information on specific financial dealings. Those representing his years with D. W. Rich & Company are mainly letters exchanged with members of the firm while he was on military leave during the World War II. The letters kept him abreast of developments in the office and up to date on his financial interests in the company. The papers accumulated during his years with Aubrey G. Langston & Company are more typical of the kinds of activities and duties he performed with the company. There are telex messages, internal correspondence, notices of meetings of financial associations, lists of banks and corporations for which Aubrey G. Langston & Company purchased securities, and drafts of business letters, including two that explain how repurchase agreements worked.
The subject files in the Montgomery Family Papers relate to Turkey. In May 1919 George Rediington Montgomery was authorized to accompany Henry Churchill King and Charles Richard Crane on a trip to Turkey to study political and economic conditions and to ascertain the views of the people regarding the settlement of the Near Eastern question. The papers of the King-Crane Commission consist primarily of the notes he took at the towns where the commission heard testimony. Some working papers used in preparing the commission's report and a copy of the report as published in the December 2, 1922, issue of Editor and Publisher are also included in the collection.
The treatment of the Armenians and other Christians was a recurring problem prior to and during the dissolution of the Ottoman Empire. The question of a homeland for the Armenians arose again following the defeat of Turkey and the need to settle the situation in the Near East at the end of World War I. In 1920 the Armenia-America Society was formed to secure American support for the Armenian cause. George Redington Montgomery became its director. His collection of Armenia-America Society papers documents the activities of that organization in the United States and abroad, including the final appeal of the society to the Lausanne Conference of 1923 and the trip of George Montgomery to Russia on behalf of the Armenians.
The miscellany section of the Montgomery Family Papers contains an extensive record of the family's activities. It includes newspaper clippings about members of the family, their scholastic records, memorabilia from high school and college days, diplomas, military papers, and other personal material.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Peck Family Papers, 1771-1946
Perkins Family Papers, 1832-1953
Montgomery Family Papers, 1858-1974
Container List
- Peck Family Papers, 1771-1946 (Box 1)
  - Family Correspondence, 1841-1864 (Box 1)
    Family letters sent and received.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of writer and therein chronologically.
    - Anna Peck (Box 1)
    - David J. Peck (Box 1)
    - Frank Henry Peck, 1856-1864, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Other family members (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1854-1916 (Box 1)
    Letters sent and received.
    Arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellany, 1771-1946 (Box 1)
    Miscellaneous personal items.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
    - David J. Peck (Box 1)
    - Frank Henry Peck, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Other family members (Box 1)
- Perkins Family Papers, 1832-1953 (Box 2-3)
  - Family Correspondence, 1832-1953 (Box 2)
    - Abigail Peck Perkins (Box 2)
    - Newton William Perkins, 1861-1901, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - Theresa H. Perkins (Box 2)
    - Other family members (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1862-1909 (Box 2)
  - Financial Papers, 1877-1912 (Box 3)
    Account book, bills and receipts, and financial diaries.
    Arranged by name of family member.
    - Abigail Peck Perkins (Box 3)
      - Accounts for cottage at Short Beach, Conn., and tax receipts (Box 3)
      - Financial diaries, 1904-1911, and account book, 1904-1912 (Box 3)
      - Estate of (Box 3)
    - Newton William Perkins (Box 3)
  - Miscellany, 1840-1912 (Box 3)
    Birth certificates, clippings, and military papers.
    Arranged by type of material.
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Military papers (Box 3)
      - Newton William Perkins (Box 3)
      - 13th Regiment, Connecticut (Box 3)
    - Obituaries, Newton William Perkins (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Montgomery Family Papers, 1858-1974 (Box 4-33)
  - Diaries, 1866-1927 (Box 4)
    Diaries of family members.
    - Giles Foster Montgomery, 1866, Nov. 17-Dec. 14 (Box 4)
    - Marshall Hugh Montgomery, 1927, Jan. 1-Mar. 18 (Box 4)
    - Roger E. Montgomery, 1916, Dec. 5-1917, Apr. 19 (Box 4)
  - Family Correspondence, 1874-1973 (Box 4-12)
    - Gutzon Borglum (Box 4)
    - Lincoln Borglum (Box 4)
    - Louella Borglum (Box 4)
    - Mary Ellis Borglum (Box 4)
    - Mary Montgomery Borglum (Box 4)
      - 1883-1907, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1921-1955, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Margaret M. Hanna (Box 5)
    - Estelle H. Ingham (Box 5)
    - Eleanor B. Montgomery (Box 5)
    - Emily Emerson Montgomery (Box 5)
    - Emily Redington Montgomery, 1885-1898, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Ernest E. Montgomery (Box 5)
    - George Redington Montgomery, 1885-1945, (6 folders) (Box 6)
    - Giles B. and Jill R. Montgomery (Box 7)
    - Giles Foster Montgomery (Box 7)
    - Giles N. Montgomery (Box 7)
    - Helen Perkins Montgomery, 1908-1931, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Louise A. Montgomery, 1901-1960, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Marshall Montgomery (Box 7)
    - Marshall D. and Elizabeth C. Montgomery, June 2, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Marshall F. Montgomery, 1885-1956, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Marshall Hugh Montgomery (Box 8)
      - 1918-1932, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - 1933-1945, Nov., (5 folders) (Box 9)
      - 1963-1973 (Box 9)
    - Prudence I. Montgomery (Box 10)
      - 1931-1939, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1943-1973, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - Roger E. Montgomery, 1910-1973, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - William O. Montgomery (Box 11)
    - Grace Perkins Moore (Box 11)
    - Winthrop P. Moore (Box 11)
    - Abigail Peck Perkins (Box 11)
    - Beth Perkins Richardson (Box 11)
    - Helen D. Richardson (Box 11)
    - Robert K. Richardson (Box 11)
    - William A. Robinson (Box 11)
    - Mrs. Frederick V. Ruston (Box 11)
    - John L. Tincher (Box 11)
    - Other family members (Box 12)
      - A-M (Box 12)
      - N-Y and unidentified (Box 12)
  - General Correspondence, 1858-1973 (Box 12)
    Letters received and copies of letters sent.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein chronologically
    - Gutzen Borglum (Box 12)
    - Mary Montgomery Borglum (Box 12)
      - 1868-1911, (3 folders) (Box 12)
      - 1912-1952 (Box 13)
    - Emily Redington Montgomery (Box 13)
    - George Redington Montgomery (Box 13)
      - 1879-1937, (5 folders) (Box 13)
      - 1938-1946 (Box 14)
    - Giles B. and Jill Montgomery (Box 14)
    - Giles Foster Montgomery (Box 14)
    - Giles N. and Eleanor Montgomery (Box 14)
    - Helen Perkins Montgomery (Box 14)
    - Marshall F. Montgomery (Box 14)
    - Marshall Hugh Montgomery (Box 14)
      - 1918-1947, (4 folders) (Box 14)
      - 1948-1973, (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - Prudence I. Montgomery (Box 15)
    - Roger E. Montgomery (Box 15)
    - Other family members (Box 15)
  - Business Papers (Marshall Hugh Montgomery), 1931-1974 (Box 16)
    Business correspondence and printed matter.
    Arranged by name of firm and therein chronologically.
    - New York Hanseatic Corp., 1931-1939 (Box 16)
    - D. W. Rich & Co., 1940-1949 (Box 16)
    - Aubrey G. Langston & Co. (Box 16)
      - 1951-1974, (3 folders) (Box 16)
      - Statement submitted to the United States House Banking and Currency Committee by Aubrey G. Langston, 1957 (Box 16)
  - Speeches and Writings File, 1880-1971 (Box 17)
    Speeches, book reviews, typescripts and printed copies of articles, newspaper columns and editorials, poems, and sermons.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of writer and therein by type of material.
    - Giles Foster Montgomery, lecture notes and sermon (Box 17)
    - Giles N. Montgomery, articles (Box 17)
    - George Redington Montgomery (Box 17)
      - Articles (Box 17)
      - Books (Box 17)
        - Talking English (1989) (Box 17)
        - English Language Sounds (1942) (Box 17)
        - The Unexplored Self (1910), reviews (Box 17)
        - "Visualizing in the Algebra of Logic," unpublished manuscript (Box 17)
      - Editorials (Box 17)
      - News columns in London Standard, covering Turko-Greek War, Apr. 20-May 25, 1897 (Box 17)
      - Poems (Box 17)
      - Sermons (Box 17)
      - Other writings (Box 17)
    - Marshall F. Montgomery (Box 17)
      - Speeches and sermons (Box 17)
      - Other writings (Box 17)
    - Marshall Hugh Montgomery (Box 17)
      - Articles (Box 17)
      - Some War Letters of Pvt. Marshall H. Montgomery, Italy 1944-1945 (1945) (Box 17)
      - Other writings (Box 17)
    - Roger E. Montgomery (Box 17)
    - Helen and Robert Richardson (Box 17)
  - Financial Papers, 1892-1973 (Box 18-20)
    Bankbooks, bills and receipts, canceled checks, income tax records, insurance policies, and mortgages and other property records.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein by type of material.
    - Mary Montgomery Borglum (Box 18)
    - Emily Redington Montgomery (Box 18)
    - George Redington Montgomery (Box 18)
      - Accounts for The Unexplored Self (Box 18)
      - Bills and receipts (Box 18)
      - Book orders for English Language Sounds (Box 18)
      - Deeds, leases, and mortgages (Box 18)
      - Estate of (Box 18)
      - Income tax records (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - Helen Perkins Montgomery (Box 18)
    - Marshall F. Montgomery (Box 18)
      - Bills and receipts (Box 18)
      - Income tax records (Box 18)
    - Marshall Hugh Montgomery (Box 19)
      - Bills and receipts (Box 19)
      - Contracts (Box 19)
      - Income tax records, (2 folders) (Box 19)
      - Insurance policies (Box 19)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Prudence I. Montgomery (Box 20)
    - Other family members (Box 20)
  - Subject File, 1919-1923 (Box 20-23)
    Correspondence, notes, and memoranda.
    Arranged chronologically under two subjects, the King-Crane Commission and Armenia-America Society.
    - King-Crane Commission, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Armenia-America Society (Box 21)
      - 1919-1921, (6 folders) (Box 21)
      - 1922-1923, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 22)
      - Minutes of Executive Committee meetings and annual meetings, 1920-1923 (Box 23)
  - Miscellany, 1860-1974 (Box 23-33)
    Birth certificates, biographical and genealogical notes, military papers, school records and papers, drawings, greeting cards, invitations, printed matter, and souvenir programs and other memorabilia.
    Arranged by name of family member and therein by type of material.
    - Anne Montgomery Bijur (Box 23)
    - Gutzon Borglum, Czech-Slovak Training Camp, Stamford, Conn. (Box 23)
    - Lincoln Borglum (Box 23)
    - Mary Ellis Borglum (Box 23)
    - Mary Montgomery Borglum (Box 23)
      - Clippings (Box 23)
      - Hillhouse High School, New Haven, Conn. (Box 23)
      - University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany (Box 23)
      - Wellesley College, Wellesley, Mass. (Box 24)
      - Memorabilia (Box 24)
      - Miscellaneous manuscripts and fragments (Box 24)
    - Solon H. Borglum (Box 24)
    - G. Dallas and Margaret M. Hanna (Box 24)
    - Estelle H. Ingham (Box 24)
    - Eleanor B. Montgomery (Box 24)
      - Clippings (Box 24)
      - School papers (Box 24)
      - Souvenir dance programs (Box 25)
      - Trip to Europe, June-July 1937 (Box 25)
    - Emily Emerson Montgomery (Box 25)
    - Emily Redington Montgomery (Box 25)
    - Ernest E. Montgomery (Box 25)
    - George Redington Montgomery (Box 25)
      - Biographies (Box 25)
      - Clippings (Box 25)
      - Church programs of worship and related material (Box 25)
      - Funeral and obituaries (Box 25)
      - Last will and testament (Box 25)
      - Printed material and memorabilia relating to Yale University, New Haven, Conn. (Box 25)
      - Passports and credentials (Box 26)
      - School records and diplomas (Box 26)
      - Unidentified manuscripts and fragments (Box 26)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
    - Giles B. and Jill Montgomery (Box 26)
    - Giles Foster Montgomery (Box 26)
    - Giles N. Montgomery, school papers (Box 26)
    - Helen Perkins Montgomery (Box 26)
    - Louise A. Montgomery (Box 26)
    - Marshall Montgomery (Box 26)
    - Marshall D. Montgomery, school papers and memorabilia (Box 27)
    - Marshall D. and Elizabeth C. Montgomery (Box 27)
    - Marshall F. Montgomery (Box 27)
      - Biography (Box 27)
      - Certificates, diplomas (Box 27)
      - Clippings (Box 27)
      - Estate of (Box 27)
      - Last will and testament (Box 27)
      - Tours and lectures (Box 27)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 27)